Must you go back?
どうしても帰るのか
Yeah, I would like to stay,
できることなら 一緒にいたかったんだが
but we were born and raised in Yamayura,
俺たちは 生まれも育ちも
ヤマユラだからなあ
so we would like to die there too.
だから 死ぬ時も
Aruruu, don't go eating strange things
and getting a tummy ache.
アルルゥ
おかしな物を食べて
お腹を壊すんじゃないよ
Eruruu, don't try too hard.
エルルゥ
頑張り過ぎないで
つらい時は素直に甘えること
It's okay to be seek solace
during tough times.
It is going to be lonely around here.
寂しくなるな
Yes.
はい
kodomo no goro no yume wa
The dream I had when I was a child,
子供の頃の夢は 色褪せない落書きで
iroase nai rakugaki de
were drawn to my heart's desire
omou mama kaki suberasete
with scribbles that wouldn't fade away
思うまま書き滑らせて
描く未来へとつながる
egaku mirai he to tsunagaru
and are connected to the future i draw.
Utawarerumono
sumiwataru sora
The clear skies
澄み渡る空 果てしないほど青く
hateshinai hodo aoku
were endlessly blue.
mujaki na kokoro ni
And my innocent heart,
無邪気な心に 充たされ魅かれてく
mitasare hikareteku
being satisfied, was attracted to them.
yagate jiyuu ni tobimawareru
I finally obtained wings
やがて自由に飛びまわれる
翼（はね）を手に入れて
hane wo teni irete
with which I could fly freely.
muku na hitomi wa motometeku
I want to go to the end of the skies
無垢な瞳は求めてく
空の向こうへ 行きたいな
sora no mukou he ikitai na
which my pure eyes desire.
kore tonai negai kara
If one wish could be granted
止め処ない願いから 一つだけ叶うのなら
hitotsu dake kanau no nara
out of countless others...
dare ni mo yuzuri taku wa nai
I feel that it should be to grab onto a dream
誰にも譲りたくはない
夢を掴みたいと思うよ
yume wo tsukamitai to omou yo
and never be tempted to let go.
kodomo no goro no yume wa
The dreams I had when I was a child,
子供の頃の夢は 色褪せない落書きで
iroase nai rakugaki de
were drawn eternally,
itsuwademo kaki tsuzukerareta
with scribbles that wouldn't fade away
いつまでも描き続けられた
願う未来へとつながる
negau mirai he to tsunagaru
and are connected to the future I wish for.
The Mediator
I present to you Emperor Hakuoro!
ハクオロ皇
ご出座であーる
Eruruu-sama...
エルルゥ様
Oh, right!
あ はい！ んっ
I present the following report.
ご報告申し上げます
The rebuilding of the Uppako province
is nearly complete.
ウッパコの関の修復工事
ほぼ完了いたしました
A request for additional manpower
has been submitted by Fort Atuu.
アトゥー砦では
人手の補充の申請が来ております
My lord...
若さま
Don't you need to be there?
行かなくて いいんですか？
I don't much care for that kind of stuff.
ああいう雰囲気は苦手だ
And for our final report,
では 最後の報告に参ります
"Big sister laughed in her sleep.
How creepy! "
お姉ちゃんが 寝言で笑ってた
不気味
Huh!? What is this!?
って 何よ これ
Aruruu!
アルルゥ！
グルルア グルル
And so who are the Onkamiyamukai?
で そのオンカミヤムカイとは 何者なんだ
我らの御神
ウィツァルネミテアの総本山にして
They present themselves as mediators,
under the authority of the High Temple
of our god, Witsalnemitea.
調停者を名乗っている者たちです
Mediators?
調停者
オンカミヤムカイは
The Onkamiyamukai have made it their duty
to mediate relations among nations.
国や部族間の仲介や災いを防ぐことを
自らの役目としています
そのために各地を見張り
To that end, they keep watch
over the provinces,
必要とあらば 干渉してくるのです
and intervene if it is deemed necessary.
Then that is why they are called mediators.
それで調停者ということか
It is a pleasure to meet you, Hakuoro-sama.
お初にお目にかかります ハクオロ様
I have come as an envoy of the Onkamiyamukai.
この度 オンカミヤムカイから
使節の命を授かり参りました
I am Urutori.
ウルトリィと申します
I am Munto.
ムントにございます
遠いところ ご足労をおかけした
Thank you for taking the trouble
to come all this way.
ウルトリィ皇女のお越し
恐縮至極にございます
We are greatly honored by your
presence here, Princess Urutori.
皇女ともあろう お方が 我が国に
どういったご用件で参られたのか
May I ask what brings you,
a princess, to our country?
Friendship.
友好を
Friendship?
友好？
Yes!
はい
Pardon the intrusion.
失礼します
まあ こちらには
可愛らしい女官さんが いるのですね
My, what an adorable attendant you have.
ウルトリィ殿
Princess Urutori, Eruruu is
a member of my family.
エルルゥは 私の家族です
Oh, my apologies.
まあ 申し訳ありません
Is she your queen?
皇后様で いらっしゃいましたか
No, I am unmarried.
いえ 私は独り身です
She is something like a sister to me.
この子は 妹のようなものでして
Is that so?
そうでしたか
そ 粗茶ですが よろしければ
Here's some plain tea, if you please.
Princess, unfortunately it seems we
are not quite welcome here.
姫様
残念ですが どうやら我らは
歓迎されていないようですな
It's delicious!
おいしい
ほう これは なかなかのお手前
This is quite good!
That was rather mischievous to claim
such delicious tea to be "plain".
こんな おいしいお茶を
粗茶などと ご謙遜なさるとは 人の悪い
I... I'm so sorry.
す すみません
気になさらないでください
Please don't mind Munto.
Hakuoro-sama, if you wouldn't mind,
ハクオロ様
もし よろしければ
これから城下の人々の暮らしぶりを
拝見させていただきたいのですが
we would like to see the village
and its people now.
それでしたら
わたくしが ご案内しましょう
Then I will be glad to show you around myself.
I beg your pardon, his highness has
urgent duties he must attend to.
申し訳ないのですが
聖上には急ぎの政がありまして
Then, in my stead I shall have
Eruruu be your guide.
では 私の代わりに
エルルゥに案内をさせましょう
We would appreciate that very much.
よろしくお願いします
あ はい
Yes...
My, what a lively place.
これは また盛況な
I see energy here that I have not
found in other places.
ここには 他には無い活気があります
Now that they have been released from
the oppression of tyranny,
抑圧から解放され 今は
安心して商いに励んでいるようですね
it seems the people here are fully embracing
their endeavors without worry.
ええーい！
-わあー
-こらー くそがきー！
You, little snot-nosed brats!
What do you think you're doing!?
何をするかー！
I'm sorry!
-くうー！
-ごめんなさい
It's all right. Munto won't miss
a feather or two.
いいんですよ
ムントの羽の １つや２つ
Princess!
姫様
うっふふふ
こちらが エルルゥ様の
お部屋なのですか？
Is this your room, Eruruu-sama?
は はい
Yes!
よろしいですか？
May I come in?
え ああ… う どうぞ
Yes, please do!
あ でも その こんな所に
But the place is kind of...
Pardon the intrusion.
失礼いたします
エルルゥ様は 薬師なんですね
So, you are a healer, Eruruu-sama?
Yes.
あ はい
私も薬師になろうと思って
医術を学んだことがありました
I too aspired to be a healer at one
time and I even studied for it.
You did, Princess Urutori?
ウルトリィ様が
Yes, but that was before I understood
my station in life.
まだ自分の立場も
分かってなかった頃の話です
どうして 薬師になろうと
思われたんですか？
Why did you wish to become a healer?
I wanted to help those who were hurt.
傷ついている人たちを
助けたかったからです
How about you, Lady Eruruu?
エルルゥ様は？
Well, I...
私は
My grandmother was a healer.
薬師だったんです
祖母が
She was well liked by everyone.
皆に すごく慕われていました
So I wanted to be just like her.
だから私も 祖母のようになろうと思って
ふっふふ ふふっ
キュ キュ キュ
-んん？
-ハアー
クゥ クゥー… スー
う う ふうう
うわあ！ ああ ふうう ええと…
Well...
Could it be that you can see me?
もしかして
カミュのこと見えてたりしてえ
What are you talking about?
何を言っている
Oh, no!
いっけない
All right!
よし
I should be good and invisible now...
これで きちんと消えたはず
I can still see you.
見えてるぞ
うっへへへ うう
Well, then, see you later!
うええ それじゃーっ！ ああ
What was that all about?
何だ？ あれは
What!?
何いいー！ わはあ
うっ う うっ うっ はっ くうう
Mukkuru?
ムックル？
ホッホッホ ホフ ホフ
ホフ ホホウ
にゃっ！ ごふっ ごっふう
Mukkuru?
-ムックル
-グルル
Aruruu? Why are you here?
アルルゥ
どうして ここに？
I want to sleep with Father.
お父さんと寝る
Hakuoro-sama, pardon me for
disturbing you at this hour.
ハクオロ様
夜分 失礼します
Was there a silver-haired girl here?
こちらに 銀色の髪の女の子は
来ていないでしょうか
For some reason, I am feeling a
very familiar aura here.
なぜか とても よく知った波動を
感じるのですが
Camus, come out here now.
カミュ 出てらっしゃい
えっへへ へん
Camus, why are you here?
カミュ どうして あなたが
ここにいるのですか？
Because...
んふ だって…
Because, because it's no fair, no fair!
だって だって お姉様ばかり ずるい！
Leaving me all alone at home!
カミュだけ国でお留守番なんて
What a hopeless child...
もう 仕方のない子
Hakuoro-sama, I deeply apologize
for what my sister has done.
ハクオロ様
妹のしたこと 深く おわびいたします
どのような処罰も わたくしが負います
I accept whatever punishment
you choose to impart.
ですから どうか この子には寛大な お心を
So please, have it in your heart
to spare this child.
えっ ダメだよ そんなの
No, you can't do that!
Well, I do not wish to cause a commotion
over something like this.
こちらとしては こんなことで
とやかく言うつもりはありません
Instead, may I welcome your sister
as our guest as well?
それより妹君も 客人として
歓迎させてもらえませんか
えっ じゃあ カミュも ここにいていいの？
Then it's okay for me to stay here!?
Yes.
えへっ やったあ！ ありがとう！
All right! Thank you!
あはは あははは
-あははは… えへへ…
-あ… あ ふっ
Sire, please review these as well.
聖上
こちらにも 目を通しておいてください
Right.
貴様 抜けがけするなあ！
Don't try to sneak in ahead
of me, you bastard!
おめえこそ どきなあ！
Shut up! You get outta my way!
Brother!
兄者！
Commander-in-Chief!
総大将
Move it!
どけっ
兄者 兵を増やしてくれ
Brother, please increase the
number of our soldiers!
Wait a minute!
ちょっと 待てえ！
We need to increase the mobility of our forces, so
would you increase the number of our woptars?
え これからは 機動力が戦局を左右しやす
ですから ウォプタルを
増やしてくれやせんかあ
Sire...
聖上
There is only one of me.
私の体は １つしかない
Why do I have to study here, too?
なんで こんな所に来てまで
お勉強しなきゃいけないの
あまり行儀が よろしくありませんなあ
Please mind your manners.
むー ふんっ
あは
He... Hello there!
こ こんにちは
Hey, let's play together.
ねえ！
一緒に遊ぼうよ
Well, I'm not giving up!
カミュ 負けないんだから
いやあっ
Hey, you're pretty good.
なかなか やるじゃねえか
Okay, I'll give it a try too.
それじゃ 俺もいっちょ
Hey...
なあ
What the heck was that?
あれ 何やってんだ？
Heck if I know.
俺が知るか
ん これでもダメかあ
This won't work either, huh?
むう
I wonder where she went?
どこ行ったのかなあ
Here!
はい
えへへ
Wow! She's quick!
素早い
I guess she's not here.
こっちじゃないのかなあ
Princess, aren't you supposed
to be studying now?
おや
確か姫君は 勉強中のはずでは？
Please, don't tell my sister!
お願い
お姉さまには言わないで
はは 別に言うつもりはない
I did not really plan on telling her.
Besides, I have snuck away from my work too.
それに実を言えば
自分も 今 仕事の途中で
抜け出してきているところだしな
Oh? Is that right?
おあ？
そうなんだ
Again?
また
ですか
Hey, how can I be friends with that girl?
ねえ あの子と どうやったら
仲良くなれるのかな
"That girl"?
あの子？
The girl with that big animal.
あの おっきいの連れた子
ああ アルルゥのことか
Oh, you mean Aruruu?
I just want to be her friend.
お友達に なりたいだけなのに
All right, then I will teach you a special method.
よし
じゃあ 特別に
とっておきの方法を教えてあげよう
What do you mean "special"?
とっておきって？
Exactly what I said.
とっておきは とっておきさ
-グルル
-ん お客さま？
A visitor...
えっへ ふーん
ん 食べる？
Want some?
ん？ うふふ… ん
We'll eat it together.
一緒に食べる
You mean with me?
私も？
Uh-huh.
ういい はむっ
It's delicious!
おいしい！
お客様？
Please pardon the way I'm dressed, miss.
こんな格好で ごめんなさい
My name is Yuzuha.
私はユズハといいます
I'm Camus. Nice to meet you!
あたし カミュ よろしくね
It's a pleasure to meet you.
よろしくお願いします
えへへ
Oboro, have you seen his highness?
オボロ
聖上を見ませんでしたか？
No, I haven't.
いや 見てないが
-ムント殿
-んー んー んー
Lord Munto!
いったい どうなされた
What in the world happened?
The princess...
姫様が
-あーはっははは… あはは…
-おお ほ あ
Oh?
Do you mean her?
姫様って あれのことか？
Princess!
ひーめーさーまぁーっ！
あっははは…
You're quite a worrywart, Munto.
ムントは心配症だなあ
Yuzuha-san is riding with them.
ユズハ殿も乗っておられるようだな
な 何だとお！
Wh... What did you say!?
YU-ZU-HA!
-ユーズーハー！
-あはは…
あははは ほらー あはは
ユーズーハー！
YU-ZU-HA!
うわあー あははっ
フゥー ハァー
Say...
あの
Aren't you bored here?
退屈じゃないですか？
No, not at all.
いいえ 全然
This place has an old but familiar scent.
ここは とても懐かしい香りがします
The scent of Tuskuru-sama...
トゥスクル様の香りが
祖母を知ってるんですか？
You knew my grandmother!?
Anyone aspiring to be a healer
would have known about her.
薬師を志していて トゥスクル様のことを
知らない者など おりません
I had hoped to see her again, to hear
her lectures once more, but...
もう一度お会いして
ご口授を賜りたいと思っておりましたが
我らが御神のもとに召されるとはいえ
While we rejoice in returning to our
great god, death is still sorrowful.
死者との別れは 悲しいものです
I'm sorry to have brought back
painful memories for you.
つらい思いを 思い出させてしまいました
No, I'm fine already.
いえ もう平気ですから
Anyway, that's all in the past now.
それに
もう 過去のことですし
Besides...
ん それに…
If I continue to be sad, Grandma
would only scold me.
いつまでも悲しんでたら
おばあちゃんに叱られちゃう
いいんです
It's all right to feel sad.
悲しんで
When you're sad, you should
experience that sorrow fully.
悲しい時には思いっきり
悲しみの中に
自分を置いた方がいいんです
It's not too late to move on after that.
再び先へ進むのは
それからでも遅くはありません
Hey! Mukkuru!
おーい！
ムックルー！
-グルル
-んん？
ムワーウ
Just be patient a little longer, okay?
もう少しだけ 我慢してやってくれ
クゥー スゥー
I wish the days like this could continue...
こんな日が続けばいい
Forever...
いつまでも
After meeting the people of Tuskuru,
トゥスクルの人たちと接して
I see quite well that things
are much different now
この国が 先のオゥルォに
治められていた頃とは違うこと
than they were under previous ruler's reign.
十分に理解できました
Hakuoro-sama, may I request your
friendship, now and in the future?
ハクオロ様
今後も 長き良きお付き合いを
お願いできますか
It would be my pleasure.
こちらこそ お頼みします
Aru-chan, Yuzu-cchi, I'm truly happy
that we could be friends.
アルちゃん
ユズっち
お友達になれて本当に嬉しかった
I'll come to visit again.
また遊びに来るね
See you again!
またねー！
まったねー！
炎さえも凍てついた
honou sae mo itetsuita
I seek the solitude
孤独の中求む
kokuno naka moto mu
that freezes even flames.
魂から結びつき 私を恋い温めて
tamashi kara musubitsuki
Connecting with your soul,
watashi wo koi atatamete
warm me with your love.
嗚呼 祈りの言葉がふるえ
a inori no kotoba ga furue
Ah...the words of prayer tremble...
嗚呼 弱きいのちが消えても
a yowaki no chika kiete mo
Ah even if the faint-hearted
were to disappear...
くりかえす 輪廻の流れ辿り
kurikaesu innen no nagare tadori
Following the recurring paths of fate.
終わらない世界の宿命を見つめてる
owaranai sekai no shukumei wo mitsumeteru
I gaze upon the never-ending world's destiny.
くりかえし 詠われる者達よ
kurikaeshi utawareru mono tachi yo
Oh the ones being sung continuously
守られてまどろむ宵
mamorarete madoromu you ni
be protected and sleep.
Taboo